<!--
  == For your convenience, this form can be processed by EasyChair
  == automatically. You can fill out this form offline and then upload it
  == to EasyChair. Several review forms can be uploaded simultaneously.
  == You can modify your reviews as many times as you want.
  == 
  == When filling out the review form please mind the following rules:
  == 
  == (1) Blocks such as this are comments. EasyChair will ignore them.
  ==     Do not write any text into these blocks as it will be ignored.
  ==     You can add comments to the review form or remove them.
  == (2) Write only into the tags where instructed. Do not modify any
  ==     tags and attributes, or the review will become unusable and will
  ==     be rejected by EasyChair.
  -->
<review id="3279184::1587334"
        submission="34"
        title="An Incomplete Constraint-Based System for Scheduling With Renewable Resources"
        authors="(anonymous)"
        pc_member="Petr Vilím">
<field id="434156" name="Relevance">
  <!--
    == How relevant is the submission to the scope of the conference (all
    == aspects of computing with constraints)?
    -->
  <text required="required">
  <!--
    == Enter the text for the field
    ==   Relevance
    == below. This field is required.
    -->

The paper presents a list scheduling approach used in combination of a quite involved meta-heuristic in the framework of Constraint-Based Local Search. The contribution is relevant to the field of computing with constraints.


  </text>
  <score>
  <!--
    == Select your choice from the options below and write its number below,
    == before the </score> tag.
    ==
    == 5 excellent
    == 4 good
    == 3 fair
    == 2 poor
    == 1 very poor
    --> 3
    
  </score>
</field>
<field id="434157" name="Significance">
  <!--
    == How significant are the contributions of this submission?
    -->
  <score>
  <!--
    == Select your choice from the options below and write its number below,
    == before the </score> tag.
    ==
    == 5 excellent
    == 4 good
    == 3 fair
    == 2 poor
    == 1 very poor
    --> 4
    
  </score>
</field>
<field id="434158" name="Originality">
  <!--
    == What is the level of originality of this submission?
    -->
  <score>
  <!--
    == Select your choice from the options below and write its number below,
    == before the </score> tag.
    ==
    == 5 excellent
    == 4 good
    == 3 fair
    == 2 poor
    == 1 very poor
    --> 4
    
  </score>
</field>
<field id="434159" name="Technical Quality">
  <!--
    == What is the level of technical quality of the submission?
    -->
  <score>
  <!--
    == Select your choice from the options below and write its number below,
    == before the </score> tag.
    ==
    == 5 excellent
    == 4 good
    == 3 fair
    == 2 poor
    == 1 very poor
    --> 3
    
  </score>
</field>
<field id="434160" name="Presentation">
  <!--
    == What is the level of presentation of the submission?
    -->
  <score>
  <!--
    == Select your choice from the options below and write its number below,
    == before the </score> tag.
    ==
    == 5 excellent
    == 4 good
    == 3 fair
    == 2 poor
    == 1 very poor
    --> 3
    
  </score>
</field>
<field id="409476" name="Overall evaluation">
  <!--
    == Please provide a detailed review, including a justification for your
    == scores. Both the score and the review text are required.
    -->
  <text required="required">
  <!--
    == Enter the text for the field
    ==   Overall evaluation
    == below. This field is required.
    -->

The paper deal with a fairly generic scheduling problem (SDST-RCPSP) that generalizes both cumulative resources and disjunctive resources with setup times. It describes the different ingredients of a meta-heuristic working on top of a list-scheduling approach. The perimeter of the paper is very large as it covers:
- the definition of the targetted problem
- a set of algorithms for generating a schedule from a priority list (from scratch in section 3, incrementally in section 4, or to evaluate the impact of a change in section 5)
- the description of a quite involved meta-heuristic based on local search with tabu lists and repair 
- an experimental study of the approach on 3 classical scheduling problems (JSSP with setup times, Cumulative JSSP and RCPSP)

Even if most of the ingredients used in the approach are not really new, their combination is original. In particular, the idea to couple list scheduling and Constraint-Based Local Search in order to incrementally compute the schedules looks promising. 

The main issue I see is that, probably because there is so much content to present, the paper is not very clear on some aspects and some technical choices are not motivated enough. 

In particular, concerning the justification of some technical choices:

1- It is not clear how much faster is the incremental schedule maintenance compared to a recomputation of the schedule from scratch using the precedence generation scheme presented in section 3. On the same line, the evaluation of a re-insertion (section 5) is said to have a complexity in O(nMm); this does not seem to be very fast; is it much faster than performing the actual insertion using the incremental version ? 

2- The meta-heuristic described in section 6 is very complex and involves many components. Given that the contribution of each of these components is not studied in the experimental section (it is mentioned as being part of future work), I think you should at least better describe how you came up with this approach. 

Then, concerning parts of the paper that are not clear:

1- In section 3, I do not understand the statement that "systematically selecting the pending flow that has the latest release time allows to reduce resource idle periods". For instance suppose a resource of capacity 2 with a set of activities only requiring 1 unit of the resource. It seems that if one selects the pending flow with largest realease time one will build a precedence graph that consists of a single chain of activities, and not exploit the full capacity of the resource. I'm probably missing something here, and the example that follows this statement does not help because it is more on exploiting the existing precedences of the problem.

2- It could be useful to illustrate the incremental schedule construction in section 4 with an example

3- Same thing (illustration on an example) for the estimation of an insertion in section 5. In particular, the description of the backward flows and, most of all, how forward and backward flows are combined is not clear.

4- There are many ambiguities in the description of the meta-heuristic in section 5. Maybe a summary of the algorithm with some pseudo-code could help to have the complete vision. In particular:

* The VNS first iterates on the neighborhoods NH, then for a given neighborhood it selects an activity A and then it selects a move for A. But what are the different moves for a given activity A? In particular, how do you handle the neighborhoods that are more general than just relocating A (like the ReoderToByDistToSink or even Or-Opt), what is the exact set of moves that can be performed for a selected activity A?

* In the first search phase, you say that N construction processes are performed. These N constructions processes start from scratch and are completely independent, right? 

* The description of the second phase of the search (tabu search) is really hard to follow. The Tabu list contains makespan values but I suppose that, in the end, this Tabu list is used to rule out some moves. So does it mean that moves that produced a makespan in the Tabu list are not selectable anymore? Maybe part of the problem for understanding this section is the use of very general terms like "after each application of VNS" (do you mean after each move of VNS?) or "If after tabu search the current makespan is not strictly better" (do you mean after one iteration of the search or completly after the second phase, meaning that this would be a third phase?)

The proposed approach seems quite efficient, particularly on SDST-JSSP. 

As far as MJSSP is concerned, I'm not sure you are really comparing with the state-of-the-art approaches. In particular, the approach described in [1] already improved many of the solutions produced by MV04.

For RCPSP, it is difficult to have an idea of the performance based on the 3 plots of Fig. 2 only. For instance, on the j120 graph, it seems that after 5min, about 50% of the instances have a deviation w.r.t. best upper-bound larger than 5%. I'm not sure how good it is. And for example on the instance j120_36_6 mentioned in the paper, the default search of CP Optimizer (IBM CP engine for which the automatic search is directly inspired from [1]) finds a solution of makespan 240 in less than 1mn, compared to 244 after 10 min for the approach of the paper. Of course, it is not possible to draw any conclusion from a single run on a single instance. 

[1] D. Godard, P. Laborie and W. Nuijten. Randomized Large Neighborhood Search for Cumulative Scheduling. In Proc.  Proceedings of the Fifteenth International Conference on International Conference on Automated Planning and Scheduling (ICAPS'05), Pages 81-89. 2005.
 
To summarize, I find the article describes a huge amount of work with original ideas and decent experimental results. On the downside, the paper really lacks clarity in several parts.

  </text>
  <score>
  <!--
    == Select your choice from the options below and write its number below,
    == before the </score> tag.
    ==
    == 3 strong accept
    == 2 accept
    == 1 weak accept
    == -1 weak reject
    == -2 reject
    == -3 strong reject
    --> 1
    
  </score>
</field>
<field id="409477" name="Reviewer's confidence">
  <score>
  <!--
    == Select your choice from the options below and write its number below,
    == before the </score> tag.
    ==
    == 5 (expert)
    == 4 (high)
    == 3 (medium)
    == 2 (low)
    == 1 (none)
    --> 5
    
  </score>
</field>
<field id="434161" name="Best Student Paper">
  <!--
    == Consideration for best student paper
    -->
  <score>
  <!--
    == Select your choice from the options below and write its number below,
    == before the </score> tag.
    ==
    == 1 yes
    == 0 no
    --> 0
    
  </score>
</field>
<field id="434162" name="Best Paper Award">
  <!--
    == Consideration for best paper award
    -->
  <score>
  <!--
    == Select your choice from the options below and write its number below,
    == before the </score> tag.
    ==
    == 1 yes
    == 0 no
    --> 0
    
  </score>
</field>
<field id="434163" name="Journal-First Track">
  <!--
    == Consideration for Journal-First Track
    -->
  <score>
  <!--
    == Select your choice from the options below and write its number below,
    == before the </score> tag.
    ==
    == 1 yes
    == 0 no
    --> 0
    
  </score>
</field>
<field id="409478" name="Confidential remarks for the program committee">
  <!--
    == If you wish to add any remarks intended only for PC members please
    == write them below. These remarks will only be seen by the PC members
    == having access to reviews for this submission. They will not be sent
    == to the authors. This field is optional.
    -->
  <text optional="optional">
  <!--
    == Enter the text for the field
    ==   Confidential remarks for the program committee
    == below. This field is optional.
    -->






  </text>
</field>
<reviewer>
  <first_name> Philippe </first_name>
  <last_name>  Laborie </last_name>
  <email> phi.laborie@free.fr </email>
</reviewer>
</review>
